Finding Aid for William A. Werner papers, 1956-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William A. Werner papers 1956-1998 1978-1998
Werner, William A., 1930-
2012170 Aa 2
Ann Arbor architect and faculty member at the University of Michigan's College of Architecture and Urban Planning from 1956 to 1998. Includes correspondence and course materials with an emphasis on structural principles, including load, flexure, and force; administrative files related to Werner's teaching and his role as an undergraduate program advisor; and visual materials utilized for educational purposes.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from William A. Werner (donor no. 10798 ) in June 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William A. Werner was born in Mansfield, Ohio on October 28, 1930. He received a bachelor's degree in architecture in 1952 and a master's degree in architecture in 1957, both from the University of Michigan. He became a University of Michigan faculty member as an instructor in 1956. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1961, associate professor in 1966, and professor in 1973. In addition to being an academic professional, Werner was a registered architect in the state of Michigan and began working with Robert C. Metcalf in 1955. He was also a director and member of the American Institute of Architects (AIA), Michigan and assisted with the Huron Valley AIA Chapter for numerous years.
As a professor within the College of Architecture and Urban Planning, Werner taught undergraduate courses in architectural design, structures, and construction. In addition, he served as an academic advisor to undergraduate students and worked alongside the university's Office of Undergraduate Admissions to counsel and advise current and prospective students in the architecture program. Werner served as chair of the Bachelor of Science program from 1977 to 1983 and as assistant to the chairperson of the Architecture Program. He was also a member of many program, college, and university committees.
Werner has been the recipient of multiple awards commemorating his excellence as an educator. In 1975, he received the Sol King Award for Excellent Teaching for demonstrating dedication and concern for the academic success of his students. In 1998, he received the Educator of the Year Award given by the Architectural Studies Foundation of Michigan to commemorate a lifetime of teaching architectural education.
The William A. Werner papers consist of course materials, topical files, correspondence, and 35 mm slides dating from 1978 to his retirement from the University of Michigan in 1998. The collection is a valuable resource for lecture notes, drawings, and example problems pertaining to courses taught on architectural structures. Administrative files highlight the College's undergraduate program admissions statistics and criteria. The collection consists of two series: Course Materials and Faculty Records and Correspondence.
Subjects:
Werner, William A.; Architecture--Study and teaching--United States.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning.
- Course Materials and Faculty Records
  The Course Materials and Faculty Records series is divided into four subseries: Structures I; Structures II; Miscellaneous Topical Files, and Administrative Files. All topical files are arranged alphabetically. This series contains educational material utilized by Werner in the classroom, such as coursepacks and lecture notes for two of his courses. Topical files contain sketches and example problems relating to various architectural concepts, such as flexure, force, and load. The Administrative Files subseries contains additional material regarding Werner's professional history and his retirement from the University of Michigan.
  - Structures I (ARCH 314)
    - Instructor Resources
      - Course Logistics (Box 1)
      - Lecture Notes and Coursepacks, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Example Problems (Box 1)
      - Exam Originals 1982-1996 (Box 1)
      - Exam Solutions 1982-1996 (Box 1)
    - Topical Files undated
      - Arches (Box 1)
      - Beams (Box 1)
      - Bents (Box 1)
      - Cables (Box 1)
      - Forces (Box 1)
      - Force Systems (Box 1)
      - Frames Containing Beams (Box 1)
      - Loads (Box 1)
      - Reaction: Problems (Box 1)
      - Trusses (Box 1)
  - Structures II (ARCH 324)
    - Instructor Resources
      - Course Logistics 1996-1998 (Box 1)
      - Lecture Notes and Coursepack 1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Coursepack Problems and Solutions 1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Exam Originals 1984-1998 (Box 1)
      - Exam Solutions 1984-1998, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Topical Files undated
      - Centroid (Box 2)
      - Combined Stress (Box 2)
      - Composite Force and Elasticity (Box 2)
      - Compound Beams (Box 2)
      - Deflection (Box 2)
      - Flexure: Problems (Box 2)
      - Flexure and Shear: Problems (Box 2)
      - Flexure and Shear: Quizzes (Box 2)
      - Force and Elasticity: Axial Load (Box 2)
      - Force and Elasticity: Temperature (Box 2)
      - Force and Elasticity: Quizzes (Box 2)
      - Load: Symmetrical and Uniform (Box 2)
      - Load: Quizzes (Box 2)
      - Moment of Inertia (Box 2)
      - Shear: Problems (Box 2)
      - Steel Columns: Axial Load (Box 2)
      - Wood Columns (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Topical Files circa 1982-1998
    - Basement Walls (Box 2)
    - Column Footings (Box 2)
    - Columns and Load Charts (Box 2)
    - Combined Footings (Box 2)
    - Concrete Masonry (Box 2)
    - Double Reinforced Beams (Box 2)
    - Earthquake (Box 2)
    - Exams-ARCH 434/534 1990-1996 (Box 2)
    - Flat Plate (Box 2)
    - Internal Couple Review of ARCH 324 (ARCH 434) (Box 2)
    - Moment Capacity (Box 2)
    - Moment Distribution: Continuous Frames (Box 2)
    - Moment Distribution: Lectures (Box 2)
    - Moment Distribution: Problems (Box 2)
    - Prestress (Box 2)
    - Retaining Walls (Box 2)
    - Shear: Current (Box 2)
    - Shear Wall: Problems (Box 2)
    - Slabs (Box 2)
    - Slides, 35 mm 1954-1958 (Box 2)
    - Soils (Box 2)
    - Steel (Box 2)
    - Steel Framing: Problems (Box 2)
    - T. Beams (Box 2)
    - USD Intro (ARCH 434) (Box 2)
    - Wall Footings (Box 2)
    - Wind (Box 2)
    - Wood: Lecture Notes (ARCH 444) (Box 2)
    - Wood: Problems (ARCH 444) (Box 2)
  - Administrative Files
    - Faculty Activities Records 1986-1998 (Box 2)
    - Undergraduate Program Surveys 1976-1998 (Box 2)
    - Retirement from University of Michigan 1997-1998 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains outgoing and incoming memos and letters between Werner and colleagues, faculty members, and students. Overall, the materials in this collection provide insight into Werner's teaching career, role as an academic advisor, and professional activities history as a faculty member in the Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning.
  - Incoming 1979-1999 (Box 2)
  - Outgoing 1965-1998 (Box 2)